TheChaosLegion
l want to shine on you,
and always like that dazzling sun.
l will defend you
from all the darkness.
This is the truth from my heart.
lf only our hearts could connect,
l could get you to believe me.
Even if you can't
see it now, don't lose it.
Your kindness won't be in vain.
You'll be carried aloft by the wind
to somewhere that isn't here.
You'll cross the sea and cross time,
and l know you'll blossom one day.
Whatever the day,
l'll be there for you.
l hope l can watch over you
like the sun for all time.
This is the truth from my heart.
Moribito Guardian of the Spirit
～♪
（バルサ）誰だ！
Who's there!
An egg... An egg...
（トロガイ）卵 卵…
An egg...
卵…
An egg... An egg...
卵 卵 卵…
An egg...
卵…
The egg!
卵！
Episode 5
Secret Plan,
The Blue Hand.
How did this come to be here?
何故 これが ここに
あんた 第二皇子だね
You're the second prince, aren't you?
（チャグム）バルサ…
Balsa...
Balsa?
バルサ？
Ah, so l see!
ははーん そういうことか
二ノ妃(にのきさき)も なかなか頭を使ったね
The second queen was
quite clever, wasn't she?
You were hired to be
this boy's bodyguard?
お前 こいつの
用心棒を頼まれたか？
Torogai, this boy is...
（バルサ）トロガイ師 その子は…
Oh, how lucky l am!
わしも運がいいわ
100年に１度
あるかないかって代物が―
To think that something
that might appear...
まさか 向こうから
やって来るとはね
...only once in a hundred years
would fall into my lap!
l'm going to take a quick look.
ちょっと見せてもらうよ
Master!
（タンダ）し… 師匠！
こりゃ 確かに卵じゃわい
What we're dealing with here
is an egg, all right.
これまで
伝え聞くほかは なかったが―
l've only heard stories
about these until now.
この目で拝める日が来るとはね
To think that l'd see one
with my own eyes...
W-Wait a minute!
ああっ… 待て！
やはり ナユグと折り合うのは
簡単じゃないね
lnteracting with Nayug is
indeed no easy matter...
（タンダ）師匠 あれは いったい…
Master, what in the world is...
That is the egg of Nyunga Ro lm.
ありゃあ
ニュンガ･ロ･イムの卵だよ
卵？
An egg?
What is a...whatever you said?
何ですか？ その…
A Nyunga Ro lm is a creature said
to drink the waters of Sagu dry.
ニュンガ･ロ･イムってのは―
サグの水を
飲み干すとも言われる生き物
lt's what the people of Yogo
would call a water demon.
ヨゴの連中が言うところの
水妖(すいよう)ってやつじゃな
もっとも ヤクー人は
水の精霊と呼んでおるがな
We Yakoo, on the other hand,
call it the spirit of the water.
ここに来たのは
正解だったようですね
lt sounds like l made
the right call in coming here.
トロガイ師
Torogai, can you do anything
to remove this egg or whatever it is?
なんとか その卵とやらを
取り除いてはもらえませんか？
無理じゃな
Probably not.
二ノ妃も
同じことを聞いてきおったがの
The second queen asked me
the very same question.
Nayug and Sagu overlap,
supporting each other's existence.
ナユグとサグとは―
互いを支え合うよう
並んで存在してはいるが―
But it is no simple matter
to interact between the two.
双方に折り合いをつけるのは
並大抵のことではない
lf memory serves, in the Yakoo tongue,
Sagu means "this world."
サグというのは―
確か ヤクーの言葉で
この世という意味
しからば ナユグというのは
あの世のことか？
That being the case, does Nayug
then mean "the other world"?
まったく 素人は これだから…
Honestly, this is why l don't
care much for amateurs.
（タンダ）まあまあ 師匠
Now, now, Master...
卵が産みつけられたのは
いつごろじゃ？
When was the egg laid inside you?
l have no memory of it happening...
自分では覚えておらぬが―
おかしなことが起こり始めたのは
春の初めのころじゃ
...but strange things began to happen
around the beginning of spring.
Ah, l see.
なるほど
なら 孟春(もうしゅん)の満月のときじゃろ
lf so, it must have been around
the full moon of the first lunar month.
You see, it is said that
Nayug and Sagu...
満月のとき ナユグとサグが
強く引き合うというからね
...are powerfully drawn to
each other during full moons.
How ironic.
皮肉なもんだ
水妖を退治して この国を
作ったというトルガルの子孫が―
Torugaru slew a water spirit
to create this nation.
And now his descendant
bears the egg of one...
その卵を宿し それが原因で―
...and is at risk of being killed by
his own father because of it.
自分の親に殺されるはめに
なったってんだからね
Still, that Nyunga Ro lm was foolish.
だが ニュンガ･ロ･イムも
バカだねえ
皇子に卵を産みつけたりしたら
卵が危ないだろうに
Laying its egg inside a prince would
so clearly put the egg in danger!
Tell me, how does it feel to be
a Nyunga Ro Chaga?
やい！ どんな気分じゃ？
晴れて ニュンガ･ロ･チャガに
なった気分は
Torogai...
トロガイ師 もう少し分かるように
話してもらえませんか？
...would you mind explaining things
in terms that we can all understand?
Unlike you, the rest of us
aren't schooled in the arts.
あんたと違って
私たちは凡人なんですから
しおらしく出たか
That was tactfully put.
Very well, l'll explain it so that
even a nitwit could understand.
まあいい ぼんくらにも
分かるように教えてやろう
ニュンガ･ロ･チャガってのはね
Translated into the tongue of Yogo...
...Nyunga Ro Chaga would
mean "guardian of the spirit."
ヨゴの言葉に置き換えるなら
“精霊の守り人”って意味じゃ
精霊の守り人？
Guardian of the spirit?
そう つまり平たく言えば
水の精霊の卵が かえるまで―
Simply put, it refers to the person
who has been given the duty...
それを守る使命を
帯びた者ってことさね
...of safeguarding the egg
until it hatches.
なのに このザマだよ
どうなってるんだろうね
But look what happened...
What in the world is going on?
But wait a moment...
あっ 待てよ
気分が悪い 風に当たってくる
l do not feel well.
l shall go get some fresh air.
Tanda, l am going to the Knot.
タンダよ わしは結び目に行くぞ
The Knot? The place where
Nayug and Sagu intersect?
結び目って あのナユグとサグが
出会うって場所ですか？
Exactly.
そうじゃ
今度こそ 水の民とつながって
確かな話を聞かないと―
Unless l connect with the Water Folk
and have a proper discussion...
...l think things are
going to get quite nasty.
どうにも やっかいなことが
起こりそうだからね
Get ready to set out at once!
すぐに支度をせい
With all due respect...
お言葉ですが バルサは
こんな ありさまですし―
...Balsa is injured,
and if l leave with you, she might...
俺まで ここを出ていったら…
What, are you saying
that you can't go?
何じゃ？ 行けぬと言うのか？
Well, l suppose we can't have
the egg fall into the mikado's hands.
まあ 肝心の卵が
帝(みかど)の手に落ちても困るしね
どうする？ バルサ
What is your plan, Balsa?
l've been mulling that over
for a while now.
そのことを
ずっと考えていたのですが―
Judging from the fact that no pursuers
have followed us here...
ここまで追っ手が
かからないところを見ると―
...the mikado must have chosen a
different means of capturing Chagum.
帝はチャグムを捕らえる手段を
変えたのだと思うのです
ほう
私が戦った連中は―
The men l fought were likely
the mikado's first, most powerful card.
恐らく 帝が放った
最初にして最高の手札のはず
You mean those youngsters
in the black outfits?
そいつは黒装束どもか
えっ？ よくご存じですね
l'm surprised you know about them.
Oh, they paid me a little visit as well.
それなら わしの所にも来たからね
Of course, l beat them at their own game.
もっとも 返り討ちにしてやったが
l'm impressed.
まいりました
当然じゃ
で 帝の次の手をどう読む？
As you should be. So what would be
the mikado's next move?
そうですね
Let's see. What if he told everyone
that Chagum died in the fire?
例えば チャグムが火事で死んだと
伝えてしまえば どうでしょう？
He's probably kept
his activities secret so far...
今までは 隠密に
事を運んできたはずですが―
少々 強引な手に
出ることができるのでは
...but this might free him up
to take more forceful action.
ほう して その心は？
What sort of forceful action?
Are you all right? Do you feel sick?
（サヤ）大丈夫？ 気分 悪いの？
Hey, if you touch him, you'll...
（トーヤ）
おい 気安く触ったりしたら…
Torogai doesn't mince any words,
but she's a powerful magic weaver.
（サヤ）トロガイ師は―
言葉は きついけれど
すごい呪術師なの
l'm sure that she'll
find a way to help you.
きっと なんとかしてくださるわ
That boy doesn't have the least
bit of talent for magic weaving...
（トロガイ）あの小僧
呪術の腕は さっぱりのくせに―
...but he's making fine progress
when it comes to treating injuries.
傷の手当てばかり上達しおる
どこぞの おてんばが―
Probably because a certain
tomboy was always...
ガキのころから
生傷が絶えんかったからじゃな
...covered in bumps and bruises
ever since she was a little girl.
まあいい
だが お前はこれから どうする？
Well, no matter. But what
do you plan to do now?
Look after His Highness out there
for the rest of your life?
あの皇子様の面倒を
一生 見るつもりかい？
ジグロが お前にしてくれたように
Just like Jiguro did for you?
lt's not such a bad sentiment
to try to save the lives of others...
お前の命と引き換えに
損なわれてしまった魂を―
別の人間を救うことで
弔おうというのは―
...to appease the souls lost
in the process of saving your own.
悪くない心がけじゃが
それで 今まで何人の命を救った？
So, how many lives
have you saved so far?
（バルサ）その話は もう…
Could we please drop this?
そうはいかん
救った者の代わりに 何人斬った？
No, we can't!
How many lives have you taken
for those you've saved?
10人か？ 20人か？
それとも 50人か？
The lives of ten people?
Twenty people?
Or has it been fifty?
ここを出てからは １人も…
Since l left this place, not one.
You don't say...
そうかい
２年前
お前が ここを出ていったのも―
lt was because you'd had
a fight with Tanda over that...
そのことで タンダと
言い争ったのが原因だったね
...that you left here
two years ago, as l recall.
Balsa. What you think of the
lives of others is entirely up to you.
バルサよ
お前が 人の命を
どう考えようと それは自由じゃ
But in this one instance,
you might not have that luxury.
しかし 今度ばかりは
そうも言っておれんかもしれんぞ
lf, as the legends say,
that egg hatches into a water spirit...
もし あの卵が
伝承どおり水妖となれば―
...it's highly likely that this land
will be struck by a terrible drought.
この地を
大干ばつが襲う可能性は高い
lf that happens, the number of lives
you carry on your shoulders...
そのとき お前の背中に
のしかかる命の数は―
...will include the millions of Yogo
and Yakoo people who live here.
この地に暮らすヨゴやヤクー
数百万に及ぶのじゃ
Do you still insist on protecting
the prince with those lives at stake?
それを 天秤(てんびん)にかけても
皇子を守ると言い切れるのか？
Yes.
はい
そのうえで 全て なんとかしますよ
l'll save him, and see
what l can do about the rest.
フフフ あきれた バカだねえ
What a hopeless fool you are...
（タンダ）
小屋の中にいれば大丈夫だ
You'll be safe if you stay inside the hut.
ls it nearby?
近くにいるのかい？
ええ 群れからはぐれた
オオカミみたいですね
Yes. lt sounds like it's a wolf
that's strayed from its pack.
（バルサ）
みんな ちょっと聞いておくれ
Everyone, listen to
what l'm about to say.
私は こんな ありさまだからね
Due to my current condition...
...l'm going to divide up some jobs
that l want you to do for me.
みんなに 手分けして
やってほしいことがあるんだ
私の言うとおりに事が運べば―
lf things work out
according to my plan...
...we'll be able to throw
our pursuers completely off our trail.
追っ手を
完全に振り切ることができるからね
Moribito Guardian of the Spirit
（トーヤ）みんなで
手分けしてって言ったのに―
She said she was
going to split up the work...
...so why are Saya and l
the only ones getting kicked out?
なんで俺とサヤだけ追い払うんだよ
追い払うだなんて…
l wouldn't call this being kicked out.
しばらくの間 ヤシロ村に
身を寄せるだけじゃないか
You're going to be laying low
in Yashiro Village for a while, that's all.
My uncle's house is there.
Relax. Balsa won't steer you wrong.
俺の伯父さんのうちだ
悪いようにはしないさ
そりゃ分かってるけど
l know that, but we'd do anything
for Balsa! Come hell or high water!
俺たちは
バルサねえさんのためなら―
たとえ火の中 水の中なんだぜ
水くせえよ バルサねえさん
She shouldn't be so protective of us.
何だろう？
（タンダ）さあ？
What do you think is going on?
No idea.
Excuse me, has something happened?
あの… 何かあったんですか？
（農兵）
なんだ 知らねえのか 山狩りだよ
What, you haven't heard?
lt's a manhunt.
The call suddenly came
down from the palace.
急に宮から お声がかかってよ
（タンダ）山狩り？
A manhunt?
（農兵）二ノ宮の皇子が
亡くなられた例の火事
You know about that fire that
killed the prince at Ninomiya Palace?
Yes.
Word has it that the fire was set
by some woman from Kanbal.
（農兵）あれが どうやら―
カンバル人の女が
火を放ったって話でな
Her name was Balsa
or something like that.
確かバルサとかいう名だったか
なんでも そいつを
ひっ捕らえるために―
Anyway, they said that the
manhunt forces are mobilizing...
あしたの朝
山狩り隊が出るんだとよ
...tomorrow morning to capture her.
We're covering all ground from
the Torinaki River to Yashiro Village!
鳥鳴川(とりなきがわ)の上流から
ヤシロ村のほうまで ごっそり
Tanda!
タンダ！
（タンダ）ああ
l see it. lf they're conscripting
even the farmers from this area...
この辺りの者まで
駆り出されてるってことは―
山狩りの規模は
100や200じゃ きかないぞ
...this manhunt will be more
than one or two hundred strong.
You two go back to the hut.
Tell Balsa what's happening here.
お前たち山小屋に戻れ
バルサに このことを知らせるんだ
What's the matter?
This is exactly what you wanted!
（タンダ）
どうだ？ 望むところだろ？
分かった 行くぞ サヤ
（サヤ）うん
Right!
Come on, Saya, let's go!
The Chamber of the Epistles,
from which even the mikado is barred...
（シュガ）帝でさえ 足を
踏み入れることの許されぬ碑文ノ間(ひぶんのま)
（シュガ）あっ… 古代ヨゴ文字か
Ancient Yogo script...
これ全てが碑文だと言うのか？
These are all epistles?
This must be the spot.
（タンダ）ここか？
Thank goodness. They're still here.
よかった 無事だったか
Excuse me?
ごめんください！
l'm sorry, sir.
（男性１）お客様
We're in mourning today,
so we aren't conducting any business.
本日は喪に服すということで
商売のほうは…
あっ すいません
それは承知しているのですが
My apologies. l'm aware of that...
...but l was told that if l came here,
you would hear me out.
ここにくれば
話が通ると聞いてきたもので
Hear you out?
（男性１）話が通る？
Yes. Forgive me if this seems abrupt...
（タンダ）ええ あの…
つかぬ事をお聞きしますが―
こちら
“青い手”という屋号ですよね？
...but this establishment is
known as the Blue Hand, isn't it?
お客さん その話
どちらで お聞きになりましたか？
Sir, if l might ask,
where did you hear that name?
えっ？ 知り合いだけど
Well, from an acquaintance...
その知り合いの方のお名前を
伺ってもよろしいですか？
And what is the name of this
acquaintance of yours, if you don't mind?
l don't mind at all. Her name is Balsa.
（タンダ）
かまわないよ バルサっていうんだ
そいつは 短槍(たんそう)使いのバルサか？
Balsa the Spear-wielder? That Balsa?
Yes, that's right.
Listen, you! What's your
connection to that spear-wielder?
（男性２）やい！ お前
その短槍使いとは
どういった間柄だ？
Depending on your story,
you might not walk out of here alive!
（男性３）場合によっちゃ 生きて
ここから出られねえからな！
Sir, what business does
Balsa the Spear-wielder have with us?
にいさん その短槍のバルサが
私たちに どういったご用件で？
いや なんでも―
Well, she says that she wants to
buy all of your merchandise.
こちらで扱っている商品を
いっぺんに買いたいってことだ
That's hardly unusual, is it?
別に変な話じゃないだろ？
あのアマ どういう了見だ！
Curse that woman!
ls she out of her mind?
Time after time she's
hindered our business...
（男性４）今まで さんざん
俺たちの邪魔をしておきながら―
商品を買いてえだ？
...and now she wants to buy from us?
（男性２）調子に乗りやがって
ぶっ殺すぞ こら！
Who do you think you are?
You're a dead man!
Why are you so upset by this?
穏やかじゃないな
Does it always upset you to have
someone buy your merchandise?
商品を買いたいというのが
そんなに かんに障ることなのか？
Listen, you.
（男性）にいさん
You keep casually throwing around
the word "merchandise."
気安く商品と言ってくれるが―
Do you know what sort of
merchandise we deal in here?
うちが扱ってる商品が
何か分かって言ってるのか？
いや 俺はそこまでは…
No, l wasn't told that part.
うちの商いは
人の売り買いが中心でしてね
Our business dealings center around
the buying and selling of people.
So that means that our
stock in trade is human beings.
したがって 扱ってる商品ってのは
人間ってことになりますが
How can you be so calm about this?
（トーヤ）なに そんなに
落ち着いちゃってんですか！
山狩りは あすの朝までは
やって来ないんだろ？
The manhunt forces won't get started
until tomorrow morning, right?
（トーヤ）いや そうですけど
人数は半端じゃないんですから
Yes, but we're talking about
some serious forces out there.
そうですよ
あれが一気に押し寄せてきたら…
He's right. lf they all
came at us at once, we'd...
そいつは いいね
l hope they do.
おお おいでなすった
Ah, here they are.
What's the meaning of this?
これは いったい どういうわけだ？
（男性）二ノ宮を
灰にしたってウワサのお前が―
We hear that it was you who
reduced Ninomiya Palace to ashes...
宮の刻印の入ったお宝で
うちから人を買いたいってんだからな
...and now you want to buy people
from us with palace crest gems.
Would you care to explain yourself?
訳を聞こうか
Please, come on in.
まあ お上がりよ
フッ
（男性）何が おかしい？
What's so funny?
We can pay you back for all
you've done to us right now!
今までの借りを
ここで返したっていいんだぞ
（バルサ）
へえー どうするんだい？
Oh? And do what?
Run to the palace, treasure in hand?
その宝を持って
宮にでも駆け込むかい？
l can't do that, and you know it.
そんなこと できるわけねえだろ
じゃ 商談といこうか
Then let's talk business.
How's your stock looking right now?
今 手持ちは
どんな あんばいだい？
人数にして30
l've got 30 people on hand.
ヨゴ人は数人で
あとは皆 外国人だ
A few of them are Yogo natives.
The rest are foreigners.
いいね みんな まとめて買い取るよ
Very well. l'll take them
all off your hands.
Are you serious?
What the hell are you planning?
本気か？ 何を考えていやがる？
Those gems are your payment.
l trust you'll be able to circulate them?
（バルサ）代金は そのお宝で
あんたの所なら さばけんだろ？
Just a minute, Balsa!
待てよ！ バルサ
Those gems represent
a mother's love for her child!
そのお宝には 子を思う
母親の気持ちが託されているんだぞ！
そんなことは承知のうえさ
だからこそ 今が使い時なんだ
l'm perfectly aware of that.
That's why this is the time to use them.
So, what do you want us to do?
（男性１）で どうする？
全員をここに連れてくるか？
Deliver them all to you here?
That won't be necessary.
Just unlock the door to your hideout.
その必要はない あんたは
アジトの鍵を開けるだけでいい
Tomorrow morning, set free
all of the people you're holding.
あすの朝 とらわれている人たちを
自由にしてやっておくれ
それで あんたの役目は終わり
楽な仕事だろ？
And that's the end of your duties.
lsn't that an easy job?
So that's it. l can tell what you're up to!
そういうことか
読めたぜ お前の腹が
This should be interesting.
こいつは面白(おもしれ)え
lt's going to cause no end of trouble
for the manhunt forces, however.
山狩り隊のやつらには
迷惑な話だろうがな
少しは利口になったようだね
l see you've gotten
smarter over the years.
言っとくけど 逃がした人たちを
また捕まえたりしたら―
But listen, if you recapture the people
you've freed, you'll pay dearly.
ただじゃおかないからね
You can trust us. This is business.
信用しろ これは商売だ
何をやらかしたかは詮索せんが
ほとぼりが冷めたら戻ってこいよ
l won't pry into what you've done,
but come back when it's all over.
This time for sure,
let's team up and get rich together.
今度こそ俺と組んで
一山 当てよう
やめとくれ 冗談じゃないよ
Please, let's not even joke about that.
This isn't part of the deal,
but that horse of yours...
話は違うけど あんたの馬
あの ひづめの音からすると―
Judging from the sound of its hooves,
is it a Kokkou stallion...
三国を一夜にして駆け抜けると
うたわれる 黒蝗馬(こっこうば)じゃないかい？
...said to be able to gallop across
three kingdoms in a single night?
うん？ いい耳してるな
You have sharp ears.
l thought as much.
Then l'll help myself to the horse too.
やっぱり そうかい
じゃ あれも もらおうか
ああ？ あれはダメだ
それは聞けねえ注文だ
Absolutely not!
That's one order l can't fulfill.
You owe me for this, understand?
１つ貸しだからな！
That's Balsa for you! She's amazing!
さすがバルサねえさんだ
すんげえや！
何か言いたそうな顔だね
You look like you want to
get something off your chest.
No, l was just thinking to myself
that you're as amazing as ever.
（タンダ）いや
相変わらず大したもんだと思ってさ
For as long as l've known you,
you've always been self-reliant.
（タンダ）お前は
昔から何でも１人でできちまう
でも…
こんなときくらい俺を頼れよ！
But...
...at times like this, you should
ask me for help, damn it!
（男性５）出ろ お前らは自由だ
Get out.
You're free.
As l sat huddled and alone, holding
back the tears on those nights...
When it felt like l was about
to succumb to my doubts...
...there you were,
at my side before l knew it.
lt was none other than you
who was there for me.
l keep wishing, "l want to be strong."
l stumble and hurt myself again.
But because l have you to believe in,
l can get back to my feet.
l simply want to tell
my dear one, "Thank you."
At the top of my lungs,
again and again.
l call out to my precious loved one.
ls my voice reaching you?
ln this world that always changes,
human warmth never does.
l'm certain l sensed the presence
of the one that l hold dear.
～♪
Next Time
The secret plan is a success...
...and Balsa slips past the manhunt.
Or rather, it appeared that she did.
Next time,
"To Die in the Misty Blue."
Episode 6
To Die in the Misty Blue
Two bodies vanish into the ravine...